Rohit Modee.

¶ International Institute of Information Technology (IIIT-H), Hyderabad - 500 032, India

☑ rohit.m@research.iiit.ac.in

У @RohitModee

in Rohit Modee

☑ rohit.modee@gmail.com

https://rohitmodee.github.io/

Summary

I am a computational chemist and machine learning researcher focusing on atomistic simulations, molecular geometry optimization, and 3D-structure generation. Some of my work includes 3D structures generation using reinforcement learning, benchmarking deep neural network potentials, and developing reinforcement learning methods for molecular geometry optimization. I am passionate about applying my skills to solve real-world problems in drug discovery, materials science, and environmental sustainability.

Education

2018 - · · · ·

Ph.D., International Institute of Information Technology (IIIT), Hyderabad, India.

CGPA - 9.13/10.

Thesis title: Machine learning in molecular geometry optimization and 3D structure generation

Supervisor: Prof. U. Deva Priyakumar

2010 - 2015

M.Tech. (Integrated) in Biotechnology, D.Y. Patil School of Biotechnology and Bioinformatics, Mumbai, India.

Percentage 69%.

Thesis title: Electron Beam Treatment: Enhancing Fish Shelf Life and Minimizing Bacterial

2008 - 2010

H.S.C 10+2, S.I.W.S college of science and commerce, Mumbai, India. Percentage 70%.

Work Experience

2015 - 2017

Junior Research Fellow (JRF), International Institute of Information Technology (IIIT), Hyderabad, India.

Principal Investigators (PIs): Prof. Abhijit Mitra, Dr. Nita Parekh, et. al.

As part of the team, I contributed to the development and testing of scripts and algorithms for the Computational Core for Plant Metabolomics (CCPM) web application which serves as a Laboratory Information Management System (LIMS) for processing large volumes of plant metabolomics data.

WebApp: http://metabolomics.iiit.ac.in/wiki/about

2015 - 2015

Dissertation Project, Board of Radiation & Isotope Technology (BRIT-BARC), Navi Mumbai, India.

Principal Investigators (PIs): Dr. K.P. Rawat and Dr. Chanda Arjun.

Conducted a research study on the use of 5MeV Electron Beam (EB) treatment for commercial sterilization of lab plastic consumables and depyrogenation of glass vials. Successfully stored basa fish at 3°C using EB treatment, resulting in lower storage costs and power consumption.

Research Publications

- **R. Modee**, S. Mehta, S. Laghuvarapu, and U. D. Priyakumar, "OptNet: Autonomous Molecular Geometry Optimization Using Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning", (2023), in press.
- **R. Modee**, A. Verma, K. Joshi, and U. D. Priyakumar, "MeGen Generation of gallium metal clusters using Reinforcement Learning", Machine Learning: Science and Technology (2023).
- D. B. Korlepara, C. S. Vasavi, S. Jeurkar, P. K. Pal, S. Roy, S. Mehta, S. Sharma, V. Kumar, C. Muvva, B. Sridharan, A. Garg, **R. Modee**, A. P. Bhati, D. Nayar, and U. D. Priyakumar, "PLAS-5k: Dataset of Protein-Ligand Affinities from Molecular Dynamics for Machine Learning Applications", Sci. Data **9**, 1–10 (2022).
- **R. Modee**, S. Laghuvarapu, and U. D. Priyakumar, "Benchmark study on deep neural network potentials for small organic molecules", J. Comput. Chem. **43**, 308–318 (2022).
- **R. Modee**, S. Agarwal, A. Verma, K. Joshi, and U. D. Priyakumar, "DART: Deep learning enabled topological interaction model for energy prediction of metal clusters and its application in identifying unique low energy isomers", Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys. **23**, 21995–22003 (2021).

Skills

Languages Reading, writing and speaking competencies for English, Hindi and Marathi. Speaking competencies for Telugu and Kannada.

Coding Python, R, PyTorch, LTFX, Basic knowledge C/C++, Perl, Bash, UNIX.

Scientific Tools RDKit, ASE, CHARMM & CHARMM-GUI, NAMD, Gaussian & GaussView, Packmol, VMD, Avogadro.

Databases Basic knowledge of Mysql, sqlite.

Web Dev HTML, css, JavaScript, Apache Web Server.

Misc. Academic research, teaching, training, and consultation.

Conferences

Talk

Machine Learning for Molecular Sciences (ML4Science), 2023
International Institute of Information Technology (IIIT), Hyderabad, India.
Talk on "MeGen: Generation of Gallium Metal Clusters Using Reinforcement Learning."

2022 Molecular Simulation: Focus on Method

Tata Institute of Fundamental Research (TIFR), Hyderabad , India.
Talk on "OptNet: Molecular Geometry Optimization Using Reinforcement Learning."

Poster

Designing Catalysts on Computers (DCC)

Indian Association for the Cultivation of Science (IACS), Kolkata, West Bengal.

Presented poster titled:- "OptNet: Molecular Geometry Optimization Using Reinforcement Learning."

The virtual 3rd RSC-BMCS / RSC-CICAG Artificial Intelligence in Chemistry.

Presented poster titled:- "Neural network potentials for representing potential energy surface and their applicability for geometry optimization."

Conferences (continued)

Machine learning how to coarse-grain, CECAM.

Co-organised by Dr. Denis Andrienko (Max Planck Institute for Polymer Research) and Dr. Tristan Bereau (University of Amsterdam).

- Workshop and Symposium on Advanced Simulation Methods: DFT, MD and Beyond.
 Indian Institute of Technology (IIT) Delhi, New Delhi, India.

 Presented poster titled:- "Cosolvents Effect on Protein (Un)Folding Equilibrium."
 - Indian Peptide Society (IPS) 7th Symposium.

 Birla Institute of Technology and Science (BITS) Pilani, Hyderabad, India.

 Presented poster titled:- "Synergistic Play of Cosolvents in Protein Folding/Unfolding Equilibrium."
 - Machine Learning For Science (ML4Science).
 International Institute of Information Technology (IIIT), Hyderabad, India.

Awards and Achievements

- Awarded the prize for best method in a machine learning hackathon focused on property prediction using SMILES at the ML4Science-2023 Meeting.
- Awarded four year scholarship for Ph.D. by TCS Research Scholar Program (RSP) 2019.
- Qualified GATE-2015 in biotechnology with 85.54 percentile (All India Rank (AIR) 1290).

Miscellaneous Experience

Teaching Assistant-ship (IIIT)

- **■** Data Driven Drug Discovery
- Advanced Biomolecular Architecture
- **■** Introduction to Biology

Scientific Meeting Organised

- Member of organising team, "Machine Learning for Science: Symposium and Discussion Meeting" Held in Nov 2019, IIIT Hyderabad
- Member of organising team, INDO-GERMAN Workshop on "Computing in Chemistry, Biology and Medicine" Held in Nov 2017, IIIT Hyderabad.
- Member of organising team, CCPM Workshop 6 "Conversation with Experimentalists" held in Feb 2016, IIIT-Hyderabad.

Miscellaneous Experience (continued)

Other Projects

Effect of cosolvent on protein un-folding (U/F), International Institute of Information Technology (IIIT), Hyderabad, India (Not published).

Authors - Rohit Modee and Prof. U. Deva Priyakumar

We studied thermal denaturation and reversible U/F equilibrium of trpzip1 monomeric β -hairpin protein in binary (water + urea) and ternary (water + urea + TMAO) solution. We performed all-atom replica exchange MD (REMD) simulations. Results show that hydrogen bonds play an important role in forming a β -hairpin structure, along with van der Waals (vdW) interactions. We found disruption of intramolecular hydrogen bonds in the presence of urea.

References

Prof. U. Deva Priyakumar

Professor & HOD,

Center for Computational Natural Sciences and Bioinformatics (CCNSB), International Institute of Information Technology (IIIT), Gachibowli, Hyderabad-500032, India.

✓ deva@iiit.ac.in

Prof. Abhijit Mitra

Professor (Retired),

Center for Computational Natural Sciences and Bioinformatics (CCNSB), International Institute of Information Technology (IIIT),

Gachibowli, Hyderabad-500032, India.

☑ abi_chem@iiit.ac.in, and abichem@gmail.com

Prof. Gopalakrishnan Bulusu

Adjunct Professor at IIIT-Hyderabad,

Consultant at TCS Research,

Adjunct Professor at Dr. Reddy's Institute of Life Sciences (DRILS),

Head, Academic Programs, iHub-Data,

Gachibowli, Hyderabad-500032, India.

☑ gopal@iiit.ac.in